NARRATOR: Welcome to the Harry Potter
Magical Movie Mode,
a wondrous new way to experience
Harry Potter and the Philosopher's Stone
As you enjoy the movie
and join Harry, Ron, and Hermione
for their first year at Hogwarts,
a spell-binding collection
of fun and curious events await.
Discover filmmaking secrets and stories
from the set with director Chris Columbus.
Bewitching treats and treasures,
exploring everything from powerful charms
to fantastic foods, to mythical beasts,
delight and dazzle you at every turn.
And when you spy the Portkey
in the corner of the screen,
you'll be transported
to an amazing deleted or extended scene.
But that's only half the magic.
Along the way, play the Hogwarts Trivia Challenge
and put your Harry Potter knowledge to the test.
It's simple. Sort yourself
into your favorite Hogwarts house.
Then with quill and parchment,
prepare to track your score.
Earn five points for every trivia question
you answer correctly.
As a bonus, if you catch a glimpse
of the Golden Snitch gliding,
or even hiding in a scene
where it shouldn't be,
give yourself an additional 25 points.
Be certain to stay after the film for
the house cup ceremony to see how you've done.
So give it your best go.
You might even win the house cup.
Now start yourjourney
and let the magic begin.
Hi, I'm Chris Columbus.
I'm here to walk you through
some of the more exciting scenes
from Harry Potter and the Sorcerer's Stone,
or, if you're in England,
Harry Potter and the Philosopher's Stone.
A lot of these scenes bring back
some amazing memories for me,
and I hope they bring back some good memories
for you from when you first saw the film.
[CAT MEOWS]
I should've known that you would
be here, Professor McGonagall.
Good evening, Professor Dumbledore.
Are the rumors true, Albus?
I'm afraid so, professor.
The good and the bad.
- And the boy?
- Hagrid is bringing him.
Is it wise to trust Hagrid
with something so important?
Professor, I would trust Hagrid
with my life.
[ENGINE ROARS]
Professor Dumbledore, sir.
Professor McGonagall.
- No problems, I trust, Hagrid?
- No, sir.
We're gonna first start in a scene
where Harry is delivered
onto the Dursleys' front porch by Dumbledore,
and this is an interesting scene,
because we actually had
to film the scene with a real baby
and we found some triplets
who were able to work in 20-minute increments.
And I just remember the one distinct thing
I remember about shooting this scene,
is that the baby was such
a very jumpy, nervous sleeper,
that we had to walk around
on our tiptoes and whisper,
so you had a film crew of 150 people
whispering throughout this entire scene.
It's probably the most quiet scene
I've ever filmed.
And then there was the problem
of actually applying Harry's scar,
which was fresh at this point in the story.
It just happened.
Applying Harry's scar
onto the forehead of the baby
was something that was impossible to do.
We just couldn't apply prosthetics to the baby.
So the scar was actually digitally created.
And I remember doing that close-up of the baby,
we needed to just be extraordinarily quiet.
And it took us several takes because
the baby was always waking up and crying.
It was actually one of the most calm nights
I've ever had on a film shoot,
because everyone was pleasant and whispering.
And we came up with this idea
when we were shooting the film
that it would be great to use the scar
as a transition between baby Harry
and when we first introduce
Daniel Radcliffe into the film.
WOMAN:
Up. Get up!
Now!
DUDLEY: Wake up, cousin!
We're going to the zoo!
PETUNIA: Here comes the birthday boy.
VERNON: Happy birthday, son.
Cook breakfast.
And try not to burn anything.
- Yes, Aunt Petunia.
- I want everything to be perfect...
...for my Dudley's special day!
- Hurry up! Bring my coffee, boy.
- Yes, Uncle Vernon.
PETUNIA:
Aren't they wonderful, darling?
- How many are there?
- 36. Counted them myself.
36?! But last year I had 37!
- But some are bigger than last year's.
- I don't care!
This is what we're going to do.
We're going to buy you two
new presents. How's that, pumpkin?
PETUNIA: It should be a lovely day
at the zoo. I'm looking forward to it.
I'm warning you now, boy.
Any funny business, any at all...
...and you won't have
any meals for a week.
Get in.
DUDLEY:
Make it move.
Move!
- Move!
- He's asleep!
He's boring.
Sorry about him. He doesn't understand
what it's like, lying there...
...watching people press
their ugly faces in on you.
Can you hear me?
It's just, I've never talked
to a snake before.
Do you...?
Do you talk to people often?
You're from Burma, aren't you?
Was it nice there?
Do you miss your family?
I see. That's me as well.
I never knew my parents either.
Mummy, Dad, you won't believe
what this snake is doing!
Thanks.
Anytime.
MAN:
Snake!
[SCREAMING]
Mum! Mummy! Help me!
My darling boy!
How did you get in there?
Who did this? How did you get
in there? Is there a snake?
It's all right, sweetheart.
We'll get you out of these cold clothes.
- What happened?
- I swear, I don't know!
The glass was there
and then it was gone, like magic.
There's no such thing as magic.
PETUNIA:
And smile!
Oh! Vernon, just look at him.
I can't believe it.
In just a week, he'll be off to Smeltings.
Caveat Smeltonia. Proudest moment of my life.
Will I have to wear that too?
PETUNIA:
What? You go to Smeltings?
Don't be so stupid.
You're going to go to the state school
where you belong.
This is what you're going to be wearing
when I finish dyeing it.
But that's Dudley's old uniform.
It'll fit me like bits of old elephant skin.
It'll fit you well enough.
Now go get the post. Go!
VERNON:
Marge is ill. Ate a funny whelk.
- Dad, look! Harry's got a letter!
- It's mine!
Yours? Who'd be writing to you?
[DRILL WHIRS]
VERNON:
No more mail through this letterbox.
PETUNIA:
Have a lovely day at the office, dear.
[OWL HOOTS]
Shoo! Go on.
[OWLS SHRIEKING]
[SCREAMS]
Fine day, Sunday.
In my opinion, best day of the week.
Why is that, Dudley?
- Because there's no post on Sundays?
- Right you are, Harry!
No post on Sunday.
Now we have the mail delivery scene here.
It was one of my favorite sequences in the film.
Why? Because we didn't resort
to digital effects.
We did when the owls arrive at Privet Drive.
We probably had four or five real owls,
and we supplemented the scene
by adding all these digital owls.
But every shot of the letters
that arrive through the fireplace
was done practically.
Now, today, even six, seven, eight years later,
we would have done this by creating CGI letters
and having the actors react to nothing.
But I thought it would be great
if they had something tangible to react to.
So we had our crack special effects supervisor,
John Richardson,
come up with this method
of using an air shaft
to blow hundreds of letters
through the fireplace.
And it worked beautifully.
I, even, was fortunate enough to operate
one of the three cameras in this sequence,
so it's something I'm proud of.
Even though I direct films,
I would love to someday be a camera operator.
For me, it was fantastic.
Every shot you see here,
these are all filled with real, practical letters.
And I love this sequence
because you see, for the first time in the movie,
there's a sense of joy and happiness
in Harry Potter's face.
That's sort of the first time he feels
any sort of happiness in his life.
So, that's one of the other reasons
I really love this scene.
Daddy's gone mad, hasn't he?
Make a wish, Harry.
Hagrid's arrival, to basically free Harry
and tell Harry, for the first time, he's a wizard,
this was quite a difficult scene to shoot,
because we actually had to build
two of these huts.
One of the huts was practical-sized
for all of the actors to work in,
with the exception of Robbie Coltrane,
who was playing the giant Hagrid.
All of Robbie's material was shot
in a smaller hut,
so when Robbie himself, dressed as Hagrid,
walked through the door,
he appeared to be nine-feet tall.
And we shot all of the reverses
with the Dursleys and Harry
using a giant double
that we created for a former rugby player,
who has played Hagrid's double
in almost every film, I think.
And we created this wonderful
prosthetic mask.
So in long shots and wide shots,
if you're interested in seeing exactly how
we put this together,
you can actually see Harry walking,
sometimes walking through the streets of London,
with this double.
If you look close enough,
you can see the mask.
We only used it very sparingly.
When Hagrid walks through the door,
for instance,
we actually shot all of Robbie's things
on the smaller set.
So this was an interesting moment
of directing for me,
because I actually had to get
a performance out of Daniel Radcliffe,
who should have been
emotionally moved at this point.
Yet at the same time, he couldn't connect
with the other actor in the room, Robbie Coltrane.
And that was a little difficult
because he was reacting
to a guy basically in a Hagrid mask.
So it was a complex puzzle piece
to put together.
In the end, I thought it all worked out well.
It's just a wonderful moment.
This is what happens when you work
with younger, inexperienced actors.
It's a wonderful moment
with Daniel Radcliffe there,
when he finds out
that he's a wizard for the first time.
It's just, again, this sort of joy
on his face. It's just fantastic.
It comes from the fact
that he had no acting lessons.
He was really experiencing
that feeling in a real way.
Rubeus Hagrid, Keeper of Keys
and Grounds at Hogwarts.
- Of course, you know about Hogwarts.
- Sorry, no.
Didn't you ever wonder where
your mum and dad learned it all?
Learned what?
You're a wizard, Harry.
- I'm a what?
- A wizard.
A good one, I'd wager,
once you're trained up.
No, you've made a mistake.
I mean...
...I can't be a wizard.
I mean, I'm just Harry. Just Harry.
Well, Just Harry, did you ever
make anything happen?
Anything you couldn't explain,
when you were angry or scared?
Hm.
HARRY: "Dear Mr. Potter,
We are pleased to accept you...
...at Hogwarts School
of Witchcraft and Wizardry."
He will not be going! We swore
we'd put a stop to all this rubbish.
You knew? You knew all along
and you never told me?
Of course we knew.
How could you not be?
My perfect sister being who she was.
My mother and father were so proud
the day she got her letter.
"We have a witch in the family.
Isn't it wonderful?"
I was the only one to see her
for what she was.
A freak!
Then she met that Potter,
and then she had you...
...and I knew you would be the same.
Just as strange, just as abnormal.
And then she got herself blown up,
and we got landed with you.
Blown up? You told me
my parents died in a car crash.
A car crash? A car crash killed
Lily and James Potter?
PETUNIA: We had to say something.
- It's an outrage! A scandal!
He'll not be going.
A great Muggle like you
is going to stop him?
Muggle?
Non-magic folk. This boy's had
his name down since he were born.
He's going to the finest school
of witchcraft and wizardry.
He'll be under the finest headmaster
Hogwarts has seen, Albus Dumbledore.
I will not pay to have a crackpot
old fool teach him magic tricks.
Never insult Albus Dumbledore...
...in front of me.
I'd appreciate it if you didn't tell
anyone at Hogwarts about that.
- I'm not allowed to do magic.
- Okay.
We're a bit behind schedule.
Best be off.
Unless you'd rather stay, of course.
"First-year students will require
three sets of plain work robes,
one wand..."
Essential bit of equipment, Harry.
"One pair of dragonhide gloves."
Hagrid, do they mean from a real dragon?
Well, they don't mean a penguin, do they?
- Blimey, I'd love a dragon.
- You'd like a dragon?
Vastly misunderstood beasts, Harry.
Vastly misunderstood.
HARRY:
"All students must be equipped with...
...one standard size 2
pewter cauldron...
...and may bring, if they desire,
either an owl, a cat or a toad."
Can we find all this in London?
If you know where to go.
Ah, Hagrid! The usual, I presume?
No, thanks, Tom.
I'm on official Hogwarts business.
Just helping Harry buy
his school supplies.
Bless my soul. It's Harry Potter!
Welcome back, Mr. Potter.
Welcome back.
Doris Crockford. I can't believe
I'm meeting you at last.
Harry Potter. Can't tell you
how pleased I am to meet you.
Hello, professor. I didn't see you.
Professor Quirrell will be your
Defense Against the Dark Arts teacher.
Oh, nice to meet you.
Fearfully fascinating subject.
Not that you need it, eh, Potter?
Yes, well, must be going now.
Lots to buy.
HARRY:
Goodbye.
- See, Harry? You're famous.
- But why am I famous?
All those people,
how is it they know who I am?
I'm not sure I'm the right person
to tell you that.
Here we have the Diagon Alley sequence,
which is one of my favorite sequences in the film.
It's fantastic because we actually created
this entire Diagon Alley set
on a soundstage in Leavesden.
Although, calling it a soundstage
is really not appropriate
since there were leaks,
we would always hear rain coming through,
we could always hear planes
flying overhead,
but it worked for us in terms
of the amount of space to build the set.
But this Diagon Alley set
was really a wonderful thing,
when we'd bring visitors to the set,
because it was part of our Harry Potter World,
you know, when we brought school kids to visit.
You could actually walk
down these cobblestone streets.
I really wanted Diagon Alley to have
this sort of warped, Dickensian feel,
and to feel as if it had existed
for hundreds of years.
So, this is really a major achievement
from our production designer, Stuart Craig,
who I think did a brilliant job
in his attention to detail in terms
of all these wizard shops
that exist on Diagon Alley.
It had to feel like a place
you had never been to before.
And we see it through Harry's eyes
which was my feeling about the whole film.
It just had to happen
through Harry's point of view.
BOY 1:
It's a world-class racing broom.
In this particular moment, there's my son,
my son who is much older now,
looking at the Nimbus 2000 in the window.
So, it's sort of like having
very expensive home movies for me to look at.
But how am I to pay for all this?
I haven't any money.
There's your money.
Gringotts, the wizard bank.
Ain't no safer place, not one.
Except perhaps Hogwarts.
Hagrid, what exactly are these things?
They're goblins. Clever as they come,
but not the most friendly of beasts.
Best stay close.
[HAGRID CLEARS THROAT]
Mr. Harry Potter wishes
to make a withdrawal.
And does Mr. Harry Potter
have his key?
Wait a minute.
Got it here somewhere.
Ha! There's the little devil.
And there's something else as well.
Professor Dumbledore gave me this.
It's about you-know-what
in vault you-know-which.
Very well.
Vault 687.
Lamp, please.
Key, please.
Did you think your parents
would leave you with nothing?
GOBLIN: Vault 713.
HARRY: What's in there, Hagrid?
HAGRID: Can't tell you.
Hogwarts business. Very secret.
GOBLIN:
Stand back.
Best not to mention this to anyone.
I still need a wand.
You want Ollivanders.
There ain't no place better.
Run along there and wait.
I got one more thing to do.
Here we have a scene that was
a real joy to shoot, Ollivanders Wand Shop.
And the great thing
about this particular scene,
it's the first time and the only time
that JK Rowling showed up
at the set to visit.
It was her only day there,
so I was a little nervous.
I walked her through Diagon Alley,
and she loved it.
She loved-- again, the attention to detail
that our production designer, Stuart Craig,
paid to every single shop.
Even if we weren't going inside
these particular shops,
there was an attention to detail to the shelves,
to the things that existed on the shelves.
All of these boxes were individually made,
hand-printed, stamped,
with the Ollivander Wand Shop logo.
It was just unbelievable.
...that your mother and father were
in here buying their first wands.
Here we are.
Give it a wave.
Apparently not.
Another great thing about the Harry Potter films
is you get an opportunity to work with actors
who would never consider
coming in to do one or two days' work.
In this particular situation,
John Hurt, who was a fan of the books,
agreed to play Ollivander
for just a couple of days.
You don't see that in films a lot.
And so, it was wonderful
getting a chance to work
with one of my favorite British actors.
And also, again, in this Potter film,
this early Potter film,
one of the things I love about it is
its sort of old-fashioned charm.
A lot of these visual effects
in this particular sequence
were, again, done practically.
We didn't just resort to saying,
"Okay, let's do them by digital effects.
Let's use CGI." We didn't do it here.
When Harry first gets the wand,
we wanted to create this magical moment
and feeling of power with the wand.
Well, that was created
by slowing the frame rate.
Film usually runs at 24 frames per second.
And we slowed the frame rate down
to 120 frames per second,
created a sense of smoke,
blew some wind through Harry's hair.
And thought, "If this works, we'll use it.
If not, we may need to enhance it
with digital effects."
It worked beautifully.
It created a sense of you being there.
And I love creating tangible effects in films,
because it really harkens back
to the old days of filmmaking.
And for me, this scene is...
We could have filled it with visual effects.
But it's all about the performances
of the two actors.
Just one other.
It is curious that you should
be destined for this wand...
...when its brother gave you that scar.
And who owned that wand?
We do not speak his name.
The wand chooses
the wizard, Mr. Potter.
It's not always clear why.
But I think it is clear...
...that we can expect
great things from you.
After all, He-Who-Must-Not-Be-Named...
...did great things.
Terrible...
...yes, but great.
[KNOCKING]
HAGRID:
Harry! Harry!
Happy birthday.
HARRY:
Wow.
You all right, Harry?
You seem very quiet.
He killed my parents, didn't he?
The one who gave me this.
You know, Hagrid. I know you do.
First, and understand this
because it's very important:
Not all wizards are good.
Some of them go bad.
A few years ago...
...there was a wizard who went as bad
as you can go. His name was V--
- His name was V--
- Maybe if you wrote it down?
No, I can't spell it.
- All right, Voldemort.
- V o I d e m o rt?
Shh.
It was dark times, Harry.
Voldemort started
to gather some followers.
Brought them over to the Dark Side.
Anyone that stood up to him
ended up dead.
Your parents fought against him.
But nobody lived once
he decided to kill them.
Nobody, not one.
Except you.
Me? Voldemort tried to kill me?
Yes. That ain't no ordinary cut
on your forehead, Harry.
A mark like that only comes from being
touched by a curse, an evil curse.
What happened to V--?
To You-Know-Who?
Well, some say he died.
Codswallop, in my opinion.
Nope, I reckon he's out there still...
...too tired to carry on.
But one thing's certain. Something
about you stumped him that night.
That's why you're famous.
That's why everybody knows your name.
You're the boy who lived.
What are you looking at?
Blimey, is that the time?
I'm gonna have to leave you.
Dumbledore will be wanting his--
Well, he'll be wanting to see me.
Your train leaves in 10 minutes.
Here's your ticket. Stick to your ticket,
that's very important.
"Platform 9 3/4"?
But, Hagrid, there must be a mistake.
This says platform 9 3/4.
There's no such thing, is there?
Here we have Platform 9 3/4.
Interesting scene, because we were
sort of forced into shooting this
at King's Cross Station on a Sunday,
obviously the least-busiest day
of the week for a train station.
So we all got there early on a Sunday morning,
and this particular sequence,
my assistant and my driver and my daughter--
That is my fellow, Harry,
who drove me throughout
the first three Potter films,
so we became very good friends
and I put him in my film,
in this Harry Potter film,
and he has since been--
He was put in the second Harry Potter film,
and then Tim Burton fell in love with Harry
and now Harry's in every Tim Burton movie.
So he's still driving,
but he gets a cameo in every British film.
This presented quite a problem for us
because, again,
my desire to do visual effects here practically,
obviously are not going to work
when someone has to pass through
an existing brick wall.
So we decided to actually do this
with digital effects.
And it works very well.
It's a very, sort of, early, crude version
of someone disappearing into the wall
but it was sort of the best
we could do at the time.
Excuse me.
Interestingly enough, I love seeing
the Weasleys for the first time here.
The Weasleys are one of my favorite families
and groups of characters from the first books,
because they were poor,
they were always wearing hand-me-down clothes.
They were all red-headed.
I have a red-headed wife
and four red-headed children.
So I'm partial to redheads anyway.
And this is the first time that
Harry and Ginny Weasley meet,
and if you've read the books,
you know what happens to them.
So I think that's a very sweet,
nostalgic moment there.
Excuse me. Do you mind?
Everywhere else is full.
Not at all.
Again, if you're a fan of the books
or the films, a historical moment.
First time that the three kids
actually meet.
First time that Rupert and Dan
see each other and meet,
and the first time, I think,
Rupert says the word, "Wicked."
Which was part of his personality.
It was something he always said.
And I think still says to this day.
Wicked!
The look of the interior of the train
was inspired by A Hard Day's Night,
Beatles film from 1964, Richard Lester.
I wanted the feeling of the inside of the train
to feel exactly like the train
that John, Paul, George and Ringo
were riding in in the first 20 minutes
of A Hard Day's Night,
so Stuart Craig recreated
the look of that train.
Unfortunately, we couldn't shoot
on a real train,
so we utilized some helicopter shots
that you see here.
And then we shot in front
of a green screen.
And were able to shoot
with the kids on a stage,
as I worked very, very hard
to get their performances to a point
that I could cut them together in the film,
because they were kids,
they had not acted before.
This was one of the first times
they'd done a film.
And particularly Rupert,
he was truly falling in love
with all of the candy
he was able to eat on screen.
He thought this was the greatest day
of his acting career,
because we were just letting him eat
all this candy.
Each pack's got a famous witch
or wizard. I've got about 500 meself.
Watch it!
That's rotten luck. They've only
got one good jump in them.
- I've got Dumbledore!
- I got about six of him.
Hey, he's gone!
You can't expect him to
hang around all day, can you?
This is Scabbers. Pathetic, isn't he?
A little.
Fred gave me a spell
to turn him yellow. Want to see?
Yeah.
And when Hermione arrives,
it was the first time we saw Emma.
And we really--
Her look has changed considerably.
We were so concerned
about being faithful to the look
of what Jo Rowling had created.
And Hermione was written as someone
who had this incredibly bushy hair.
So we gave Emma this hairstyle
that I think,
along with each film, started to get
more and more glamorized, a little bit.
But anyway, I love this scene
because we really get a sense
of what happens throughout
the next seven movies,
because these kids, their personality
is defined in this particular scene.
For example:
Oculus Reparo.
That's better, isn't it?
Holy cricket, you're Harry Potter!
I'm Hermione Granger.
And you are...?
- I'm Ron Weasley.
- Pleasure.
You two better change into robes.
I expect we'll be arriving soon.
You've got dirt on your nose.
Did you know?
Just there.
Right, then.
First years, this way, please!
Come on, first years, don't be shy.
Come on now, hurry up.
- Hello, Harry.
- Hi, Hagrid.
Whoa.
Right, then. This way to the boats.
Come on now, follow me.
Wow.
In this particular shot,
Hogwarts is all digital.
Everything about it is a digitized version
of what we eventually built as a model.
And the model of Hogwarts that we built
was on an enormous stage
and it was probably 20-feet high
and about 50-feet wide.
And it was built on a model of a mountain.
And the attention to detail
to that Hogwarts model was stunning.
I'm sure it still exists
at the Leavesden soundstages.
And so we were really careful
about making absolutely certain
that the first time we saw Hogwarts,
it was extremely magical.
Welcome to Hogwarts.
Shortly, you'll pass through
these doors and join your classmates.
But before you take your seats,
you must be sorted into your houses.
They are Gryffindor, Hufflepuff...
...Ravenclaw and Slytherin.
While you're here, your house
will be like your family.
Your triumphs will earn you points.
Any rule-breaking
and you will lose points.
At the end of the year, the house with
the most points wins the house cup.
Trevor!
Sorry.
The Sorting Ceremony
will begin momentarily.
It's true then,
what they're saying on the train.
Harry Potter has come to Hogwarts.
Harry Potter?
This is Crabbe and Goyle.
And I'm Malfoy.
Draco Malfoy.
Think my name's funny, do you?
I've no need to ask yours.
Red hair and a hand-me-down robe?
You must be a Weasley.
You'll find out some wizarding families
are better than others.
You don't want to go making friends
with the wrong sort.
I can help you there.
I think I can tell the wrong sort
for myself, thanks.
We're ready for you now.
Follow me.
Another really wonderful day of shooting.
This, I remember, was the first time
we see the Great Hall.
And the Great Hall continues, to this day,
to exist at Leavesden studios in London.
And we built the entire Great Hall,
and even those candles that you see,
some of those candles are supplemented
by digital candles.
That particular shot of the sky
with the candles floating is a digital shot,
but most of those candles
were actually lit candles
hanging on strings
on a complicated pulley system
that lifted them up and down.
And when we first saw that shot in dailies,
everyone applauded
because they had never seen anything like it.
And we created it all in-camera,
so we felt really good about that.
Again, it had that practical feeling.
It didn't have that artificial quality
of visual effects,
and you actually felt as if this place
really existed.
It really brought you into the world.
I learned all of that
from watching those old pictures,
like Beauty and the Beast,
and really seeing what Jean Cocteau
did at the time
by creating this magic
out of these tangible things and sets.
It's the first time we see Filch and his cat.
We digitally altered those cat's eyes
so they would be red, as in the books.
And this is the first introduction
of Richard Harris as Dumbledore,
who actually delivers his first speech
in this scene.
When I call your name,
you will come forth.
I shall place the Sorting Hat
on your head...
...and you will be sorted
into your houses.
Hermione Granger.
Oh, no. Okay, relax.
Mental, that one, I'm telling you.
Ah, right, then. Mm, right.
Okay. Gryffindor!
Draco Malfoy.
Slytherin!
Every wizard who went bad
was in Slytherin.
Susan Bones.
Ah!
Harry, what is it?
Nothing. Nothing, I'm fine.
SORTING HAT:
Let's see...
I know!
Here is the Sorting Hat sequence.
That young lady being sorted is my daughter
Eleanor, who played Susan Bones in the films.
And for a kid who's 11 years old
and who got me into the books,
the ability to come to the Harry Potter set every day
was really a wonderful thing for her childhood.
And here we have Ron Weasley being sorted
with the Sorting Hat.
And we created a digital Sorting Hat.
There was no way, obviously,
to do this practically.
In shots where the Sorting Hat
is not speaking,
it is a real Sorting Hat.
We had about three or four of them.
I still have one back in my office.
But this Sorting Hat,
the one that Harry wears,
and the one that Ron wears
in the sequence,
was just a brim with all of these wires
and green little balls and things
on top of it.
So that particular Sorting Hat
was created in a digital environment.
And I wanted the audience to actually get a chance
to see the Sorting Hat as he's sorting Harry.
So we came up
with this wonderful 360-degree angle shot,
where we could pan around Harry's expression
as he's listening to the Sorting Hat.
I find that when you do this on screen
as opposed to just sitting there
and holding a shot,
when you actually pan around
a digital effect
and see it moving,
it creates a better sense of reality
for the audience.
So that's really what we did here.
And the Sorting Hat has
this extremely wonderful personality
that I was very pleased with.
It reminded me of the illustration
from the first Harry Potter book I had seen.
The Sorting Hat looked very much like this,
so I was very proud of this visual effect.
And when Harry finds out he's in Gryffindor,
I just think it's a wonderful moment
again for Harry.
Again, this sense of joy
from this kid who's led 11 years
of this horrific life with the Dursleys.
It's just such a wonderful sense of belonging.
He's really finding his family for the first time.
And I just find it wonderfully touching.
Your attention, please.
Let the feast begin.
Wow.
I'm half and half.
Me dad's a Muggle. Mum's a witch.
Bit of a nasty shock for him
when he found out.
Percy, who's that teacher
talking to Professor Quirrell?
PERCY: Professor Snape,
head of Slytherin house.
- What's he teach?
- Potions.
But he fancies the Dark Arts.
He's been after Quirrell's job for years.
Hello! How are you?
Welcome to Gryffindor.
GIRL:
It's the Bloody Baron!
Hello, Sir Nicholas.
Have a nice summer?
Dismal. Once again, my request to join
the Headless Hunt has been denied.
I know you.
You're Nearly Headless Nick.
I prefer Sir Nicholas,
if you don't mind.
"Nearly" headless?
How can you be nearly headless?
Like this.
Here's Nearly Headless Nick,
which was a sequence
everyone was worried we were going to end up
getting a PG-13
because Nick removes his head
in the sequence.
Working with John Cleese again,
having been a fan of Monty Python's Flying Circus
and Fawlty Towers,
it was just a wonderful opportunity
for me to get a chance
to work with one of my comedic heroes.
This is the first time
we see the moving staircase
which, to me, is really, again,
a marvel of a combination
of building something practically
and also creating a CG world.
When we first look up
and see all of the moving staircases,
obviously we could have never built that,
but we were able to create it digitally.
And it created this wonderful sense
of real magic,
but when the staircase moves
in other moments in the film,
and the kids are on the staircase,
we built a mechanical staircase
that moves from wall to wall.
GIRL 1: Look!
GIRL 2: Who's that girl?
MAN IN PICTURE:
Welcome to Hogwarts.
GIRL 3:
Who's that?
Password?
Caput Draconis.
Wow.
PERCY: Follow me, everyone.
Keep up. Quickly, come on.
Gather around here.
Welcome to the Gryffindor
common room.
Boys' dormitory is upstairs to the left.
Girls, the same on your right.
Your belongings have
already been brought up.
Made it!
Can you imagine the look on old
McGonagall's face if we were late?
- That was bloody brilliant!
- Thank you for that assessment.
It'd be better if I transfigured
Mr. Potter and you into a watch.
- Then one of you might be on time.
- We got lost.
Then perhaps a map? I trust you
don't need one to find your seats.
There will be no foolish wand-waving
or silly incantations in this class.
As such...
...I don't expect many of you to appreciate...
...the subtle science and exact art
that is potion-making.
However, for those select few...
...who possess the predisposition...
...I can teach you
how to bewitch the mind...
...and ensnare the senses.
I can tell you how to bottle fame...
...brew glory and even
put a stopper in death.
Then again, maybe some of you have
come to Hogwarts with abilities...
...so formidable that
you feel confident enough...
...to not pay attention.
Mr. Potter.
Our new celebrity.
What would I get if I added root of
asphodel to an infusion of wormwood?
You don't know? Let's try again.
Where would you look
if I asked you to find a bezoar?
I don't know, sir.
SNAPE: What is the difference
between monkshood and wolfsbane?
I don't know, sir.
Pity.
Clearly, fame isn't everything...
...is it, Mr. Potter?
Clearly, Hermione knows.
Seems a pity not to ask her.
SNAPE:
Silence.
Put your hand down, you silly girl.
For your information, Potter,
asphodel and wormwood
make a sleeping potion so powerful
it is known as
the Draught of the Living Dead.
A bezoar is a stone
taken from the stomach of a goat
and it will save you from most poisons.
As for monkshood and wolfsbane,
they are the same plant,
which also goes by the name of aconite.
Well?
Why aren't you all copying this down?
And Gryffindors...
note that five points will be taken
from your house
for your classmate's cheek.
Eye of rabbit, harp string hum
Turn this water into rum
Eye of rabbit...
What's Seamus trying to do
to the water?
Turn it to rum. Actually managed
a weak tea yesterday, before--
[EXPLODES]
[OWL CRIES]
Mail's here.
Can I borrow this? Thanks.
Look, Neville's got a Remembrall.
I've read about those. The smoke turns
red when you've forgotten something.
The problem is, I can't remember
what I've forgotten.
Somebody broke into Gringotts. Listen.
"Believed to be the work
of Dark wizards or witches...
...Gringotts goblins acknowledge
the breach but insist nothing was taken.
The vault in question, number 713,
had been emptied earlier that same day."
That's odd. That's the vault
Hagrid and I went to.
- Good afternoon, class.
- Good afternoon, Madam Hooch.
Good afternoon, Amanda.
Good afternoon.
Welcome to your first flying lesson.
What are you waiting for?
Step up to your broomstick.
Come on now, hurry up. Stick your hand
over the broom and say, "Up."
Up!
Up. Up.
Wow!
Up.
Up. Up!
With feeling.
ALL:
Up!
- Up. Up.
Up! Oh!
Shut up, Harry.
Now, once you've got hold of
your broom, I want you to mount it.
Grip it tight. You don't wanna be
sliding off the end.
When I blow my whistle, I want you
to kick off from the ground, hard.
Keep your broom steady,
hover for a moment...
...then lean forward slightly
and touch back down.
On my whistle. Three, two...
Mr. Longbottom.
- Mr. Longbottom!
- Down, down!
Neville!
Come back down this instant!
Mr. Longbo--
[NEVILLE SCREAMS]
NEVILLE:
Whoa!
Ow!
MADAM HOOCH:
Everyone out of the way!
Is he all right?
Oh, dear, it's a broken wrist.
Poor boy. Come on now, up you get.
Keep your feet on the ground
while I take him to the hospital wing.
Understand? If I see
a single broom in the air...
...the one riding it will be expelled
before they can say Quidditch.
Did you see his face?
If he had squeezed this, he'd have
remembered to fall on his arse.
Give it here, Malfoy.
No. I'll leave it somewhere
for Longbottom to find.
How about on the roof?
What's the matter, Potter?
Bit beyond your reach?
Harry, no way!
You heard what Madam Hooch said.
Besides, you don't know how to fly.
What an idiot.
Give it here or I'll
knock you off your broom!
Is that so?
Have it your way, then.
BOY 1: Nice going, Harry.
BOY 2: That was wicked, Harry!
Harry Potter!
Follow me.
You wait here.
Professor Quirrell, excuse me.
Could I borrow Wood for a moment?
Yes, of course.
[LIZARD GROWLS]
Potter, this is Oliver Wood.
Wood, I have found you a Seeker.
Have you heard? Harry Potter's
the new Gryffindor Seeker.
I always knew he'd do well.
Seeker? But first years
never make the house teams.
- You must be the youngest player in--
- A century, McGonagall says.
Well done, Harry.
Wood's just told us.
Fred and George are on the team.
Beaters.
Our job is to make sure you
don't get bloodied up too bad.
Can't make any promises.
Rough game, Quidditch.
But no one's died in years.
Someone vanishes occasionally.
But they'll turn up in a month or two.
Go on. Quidditch is great. Best game
there is, and you'll be great too.
I've never played.
What if I make a fool of myself?
You won't make a fool of yourself.
It's in your blood.
Whoa.
Harry, you never told me your father
was a Seeker too.
I didn't know.
I'm telling you, it's spooky.
She knows more about you than you do.
HARRY:
Who doesn't?
What's happening?
The staircases change, remember?
- Let's go this way.
RON: Before the staircase moves again.
Does anybody feel like
we shouldn't be here?
HERMIONE:
We're not supposed to be here.
This is the third floor.
It's forbidden.
Let's go.
[CAT MEOWS]
HERMIONE: It's Filch's cat!
HARRY: Run!
Quick, let's hide through that door!
- It's locked!
- We're done for!
Move over!
Alohomora.
Get in.
Alohomora?
Standard Book of Spells,
chapter seven.
FILCH:
Anyone here, my sweet?
[CAT MEOWS]
Come on.
HERMIONE: Filch is gone.
- He thinks this door's locked.
- It was locked.
- And for good reason.
What are they doing, keeping a thing
like that locked up in a school?
Didn't you see what
it was standing on?
I wasn't looking at its feet!
I was preoccupied with its heads.
Or maybe you didn't notice.
There were three!
HERMIONE: It was standing on
a trap door. It wasn't there by accident.
- It's guarding something.
- Guarding something?
That's right. Now, if you two
don't mind, I'm going to bed...
...before you come up with another idea
to get us killed.
Or worse, expelled.
She needs to sort out her priorities.
Quidditch is easy to understand.
Each team has seven players.
Three Chasers, two Beaters,
one Keeper and a Seeker. That's you.
There are three kinds of balls.
This one's called the Quaffle.
The Chasers handle the Quaffle and try
to put it through one of those hoops.
The Keeper, that's me,
defends the hoops. With me so far?
I think so. What are those?
You better take this.
Careful now, it's coming back.
Not bad, Potter.
You'd make a fair Beater.
Uh-oh.
What was that?
Bludger. Nasty little buggers.
But you are a Seeker.
The only thing I want you
to worry about is this.
The Golden Snitch.
- I like this ball.
- You like it now.
Just wait. It's wicked fast
and damn near impossible to see.
What do I do with it?
You catch it.
Before the other team's Seeker.
You catch this, the game's over.
You catch this, Potter,
and we win.
Whoa.
One of a wizard's most rudimentary
skills is levitation...
...or the ability to make objects fly.
Do you have your feathers? Good.
Now, don't forget the nice wrist
movement we've been practicing.
The swish and flick. Everyone.
The swish and flick. Good.
Oh, and enunciate.
Wingardium Leviosa.
Off you go, then.
No, stop, stop, stop! You're going
to take someone's eye out.
Besides, you're saying it wrong.
It's Leviosa, not Leviosar.
You do it then, if you're so clever.
Go on, go on.
Wingardium Leviosa.
Well done! See here, everyone,
Miss Granger's done it!
Splendid!
Well done, dear.
[EXPLODES]
I think we're going to need
another feather over here.
"It's Leviosa, not Leviosar."
She's a nightmare, honestly!
No wonder she hasn't got any friends.
I think she heard you.
Where's Hermione?
Parvati said she wouldn't
come out of the bathroom.
She said that she'd been in there
all afternoon, crying.
Troll in the dungeon!
Thought you ought to know.
Silence!
Everyone will please not panic!
Now...
...prefects will lead their house
back to the dormitories.
Teachers will follow me
to the dungeons.
Gryffindors, keep up, please,
and stay alert.
HARRY:
How could a troll get in?
Not on its own. Trolls are really stupid.
Probably people playing jokes.
- What?
- Hermione! She doesn't know.
[GROWLS]
I think the troll's left the dungeon.
HARRY:
It's going into the girls' bathroom.
So, here we have the Mountain Troll
bathroom scene.
This was an interesting scene,
because when Hermione is hiding from the troll
and the bathroom is smashing,
we shot all of that practically.
There were moments of the troll
that were tremendously fun.
I love the disgusting quality
of the design of the troll.
I think the troll was designed beautifully.
Hey, pea brain!
[HERMIONE SCREAMS]
Help!
When Harry is sent up onto
the troll's shoulders,
that's actually Dan being lifted up there.
That is actually a CGI version of Harry
riding on the troll's shoulders.
It's an animated Harry Potter.
If you freeze-frame some of these things
where he's being whipped around,
you'll see that we, in a computer,
created a realistic version of Daniel Radcliffe.
Do something!
And this was one of
the more funny sequences to shoot,
because Dan was being whisked out of frame
and we're focusing back on Ron
in the sequence.
And Dan was-- You know, all the blood
was rushing to his head at a certain point.
But it's a very funny sequence,
and kids seem to really respond to it and love it.
And I do love the character of the troll
when the troll is hit in the head.
It's very funny.
Cool.
Is it dead?
I don't think so. Just knocked out.
Ugh. Troll boogers.
Oh, my goodness!
Explain yourselves, both of you!
- Well, what it is--
- It's my fault, Professor McGonagall.
Miss Granger?
I went looking for the troll.
I thought I could handle it.
But I was wrong.
If Harry and Ron hadn't come
and found me, I'd probably be dead.
McGONAGALL: Be that as it may,
it was an extremely foolish thing to do.
I expected more rational behavior
and am very disappointed in you.
Five points will be taken
from Gryffindor...
...for your serious lack of judgment.
As for you two gentlemen...
...I just hope you realize
how fortunate you are.
Not many first-year students
could take on a troll...
...and live to tell the tale.
Five points...
...will be awarded to each of you...
...for sheer dumb luck.
Perhaps you ought to go.
It might wake up.
[TROLL GROWLS]
Good of you to get us
out of trouble like that.
Mind you, we did save her life.
Mind you, she might not have needed saving
if you hadn't insulted her.
What are friends for?
RON:
Take a bit of toast, mate. Go on.
Ron's right.
You'll need your strength today.
I'm not hungry.
Good luck today, Potter.
You've proven yourself against a troll.
A game of Quidditch
should be easy work.
Even if it is against Slytherin.
- That explains the blood.
- Blood?
Last night, I'm guessing Snape let
the troll in as a diversion...
...so he could get past that dog.
But he got bit,
that's why he's limping.
But why would anyone go near that dog?
At Gringotts, Hagrid took
something out of the vault.
Said it was Hogwarts business,
very secret.
HERMIONE:
You're saying--
That's what the dog's guarding.
That's what Snape wants.
[OWL CRIES]
- Bit early for mail, isn't it?
- But I never get mail.
Let's open it.
HARRY:
It's a broomstick.
That's not just a broomstick,
it's a Nimbus 2000!
But who--?
- Scared, Harry?
- A little.
It's all right. I felt the same way
before my first game.
- What happened?
- I don't really remember.
I took a Bludger to the head
two minutes in.
Woke up in hospital a week later.
And here it is, the biggest challenge
of this particular film,
the question that more people were asking me
about as we were making the film:
How in God's name are you
going to do Quidditch?
Well, we worked on it a long time.
And I think part of our concern
was creating the stadium.
As written in the books, it was sort of
your typical stadium seating.
We wanted to create
an environment with towers.
Stuart Craig and I came up
with this idea of towers,
so Harry and the other Quidditch players
could fly around something,
and we would have something
in the foreground to create a sense of speed.
You don't really have a sense of speed
when you just have the background moving.
We actually needed those towers
in this sequence
to create that sense of speed.
My dream is to see this sequence in 3D.
Someday, I would love to get the picture back
and actually restore it in a 3D version
to see it in an IMAX theater in 3D.
I think this would benefit in a big way
by seeing it in a 3D environment.
It was important to me to also
teach the audience,
those who were unfamiliar with the books,
the rules of Quidditch,
which I had to learn myself.
Reading the book six or seven times,
I never really understood all of the rules,
so JK Rowling came up
with a chart for me.
She basically gave me the rules of Quidditch,
which I still have, so I was able
to incorporate those into the film.
A lot of this we shot practically.
But a lot of this is obviously CGI work.
The only way to really get these kids
flying on broomsticks
is to put them in a CGI environment.
So we would shoot Harry
and all the individual Quidditch players
on a separate green-screen stage,
and, using motion control cameras,
incorporate them into the backgrounds
of what we see here.
I think that it was one of
the more grueling experiences
for most of the actors
who were working in this sequence,
because riding those brooms
was a tremendously difficult thing,
to create a sense of movement,
to create a sense of urgency,
and also I think, at the same time,
to really feel as if these are
real athletes playing a game.
And that was the biggest challenge for me.
I wanted Quidditch to feel like a real sport.
I'm a big football and basketball fan,
and I wanted it to feel
like it was an exciting spectator sport
and one that would really
involve the audience.
So, I think this particular
Quidditch sequence is a lot of fun,
and, again, I hope to see it
in 3D some day.
- Yes!
- Another 10 points to Gryffindor!
Give me that!
Take that side!
Whoa. Whoa!
HAGRID: What's going on
with Harry's broomstick?
It's Snape.
He's jinxing the broom!
- Jinxing the broom? What do we do?
- Leave it to me.
Come on, Hermione!
Lacarnum Inflamarae.
MAN:
Fire! You're on fire!
Go, go, go, go!
Looks like he's gonna be sick.
LEE:
He's got the Snitch!
Harry Potter receives 150 points
for catching the Snitch!
Gryffindor wins!
Oh, no.
Yes!
Nonsense! Why would Snape
put a curse on Harry's broom?
Who knows? Why was he trying
to get past that three-headed dog?
- Who told you about Fluffy?
- Fluffy?
- That thing has a name?
- Of course he has a name. He's mine.
I bought him off an Irishman.
I lent him to Dumbledore to guard--
Yes?
Shouldn't have said that.
No more questions! That's top-secret.
But whatever Fluffy's guarding,
Snape's trying to steal it.
Codswallop. Professor Snape
is a Hogwarts teacher.
Teacher or not, I know a spell when
I see one. I've read all about them.
You've got to keep eye contact,
and Snape wasn't blinking.
Exactly.
Now, you listen to me,
all three of you.
You're meddling in things that ought
not to be meddled in. It's dangerous.
What that dog is guarding is between
Dumbledore and Nicolas Flamel.
Nicolas Flamel?
I shouldn't have said that.
I should not have said that.
Nicolas Flamel.
Who's Nicolas Flamel?
I don't know.
Merry Christmas
Ring the Hogwart bell
Cast a Christmas spell
Knight to e5.
Queen to e5.
That's totally barbaric!
That's wizard's chess.
I see you've packed.
I see you haven't.
Change of plans. My parents went
to Romania to visit my brother Charlie.
- He's studying dragons there.
- Good. You can help Harry.
He's going to the library
to look up Nicolas Flamel.
We've looked a hundred times!
Not in the restricted section.
Happy Christmas.
I think we've had
a bad influence on her.
RON: Harry, wake up!
Come on, Harry, wake up!
- Happy Christmas, Harry.
- Happy Christmas, Ron.
What are you wearing?
Oh, my mum made it.
Looks like you've got one too.
- I've got presents?
- Yeah.
RON:
There they are.
"Your father left this
in my possession before he died.
It is time it was returned to you.
Use it well."
So this was another challenging sequence.
Harry gets his invisibility cloak.
It wasn't particularly challenging
to make Harry disappear.
We just had Daniel put on a green cloak.
And then we were able
to erase part of his body.
But the big challenge here
was really how we were going to depict Harry
walking through the library
later in the sequence
and see the cloak around him.
How does an audience member accept that
when we're introducing
the concept of invisibility?
So what we did, we actually shot,
which you will see later,
Daniel Radcliffe underneath
sort of a gauze, lace version of the cloak.
And it seems completely inconsistent stylistically
with the concept of invisibility.
But when you see him walking
with this cloak over him,
you immediately buy that concept.
And this was a very, very tense day
of shooting for me,
because we were allowed into this library,
the Bodleian Library.
And all of these books you see are
hundreds and hundreds of years old, one of a kind.
So we really had to be very careful.
It was the first film in a long time that
was permitted to shoot in this particular library.
When Harry-- One of the biggest moments
for the audience ironically in this film,
which is a small moment, really, in the books,
is when he opens this first book
and this face pops out of the book.
We did that with digital effects,
but it works really well.
But the audience jumped out of their seats.
The kids particularly weren't expecting
that kind of scare at that particular time.
So, again, we had to shoot this sequence
within five hours, I think, on a Sunday.
Because it was the only time anyone
had been permitted into this library.
Oh, we've got our friend Filch
coming in here.
And this guy, David Bradley,
one of the great faces of British actors.
I just loved him.
He seemed like he stepped out
of an old David Lean picture, you know?
He looks like one of those guys
in Great Expectations or Oliver Twist,
and then his voice with the stringy hair.
I used to read this book as a kid,
this comic called Creepy.
And he looked a little like Uncle Creepy.
I just love David Bradley.
He's a fantastic actor.
[CAT MEOWS]
QUIRRELL:
Severus, I...
You don't want me
as your enemy, Quirrell.
- I don't know what you mean.
- You know perfectly well what I mean.
We'll have another little chat soon.
When you've had time to decide
where your loyalties lie.
Professors. I found this
in the restricted section.
It's still hot. That means
there's a student out of bed.
Mum?
Dad?
HARRY: Ron, you've really gotta
see this! Ron, you've gotta see this!
Ron, come on, get out of bed!
- Why?
- There's something you've got to see!
Come on! Come!
Come look, it's my parents!
I only see us.
Look in properly.
Go on, stand there.
- There. You see them, don't you?
- That's me! Only I'm head boy.
And I'm holding the Quidditch Cup.
And bloody hell!
I'm Quidditch captain too!
I look good.
Harry, do you think this mirror
shows the future?
How can it?
Both my parents are dead.
How about yours, Ron?
- Ron?
- I'll be right back.
Want to play chess?
- No.
- Want to go and visit Hagrid?
No.
Harry, I know what you're thinking, but don't.
There's something not right about that mirror.
Back again, Harry?
I see that you,
like many before you...
...have discovered the delights
of the Mirror of Erised.
I trust by now
you realize what it does.
Let me give you a clue.
The happiest man on earth...
...would look in the mirror
and see only himself...
...exactly as he is.
So then, it shows us what we want.
Whatever we want.
Yes. And no.
It shows us nothing more or less...
...than the deepest and most desperate
desires of our hearts.
Now you, Harry, who have
never known your family...
...you see them standing beside you.
But remember this, Harry.
This mirror gives us
neither knowledge...
...or truth.
Men have wasted away in front of it.
Even gone mad.
That is why tomorrow
it will be moved to a new home.
And I must ask you...
...not to go looking for it again.
It does not do to dwell on dreams...
...and forget to live.
Hi, Hedwig.
Look at you, playing with your cards.
Pathetic.
We've got final exams coming up soon.
I'm ready. Ask me any question.
All right. What's the three most crucial ingredients
in a Forgetfulness Potion?
I forgot.
And what, may I ask, do you plan to do
if this comes up in the final exam?
- Copy off you?
- No, you won't.
Besides, according to Professor McGonagall,
we're to be given special quills
bewitched with an anti-cheating spell.
That's insulting!
It's as if they don't trust us.
Dumbledore again!
[STUDENTS LAUGHING]
Leg-Locker Curse?
Malfoy.
You have got to start
standing up to people, Neville.
How? I can barely stand at all.
I'll do the counter-curse!
No, that's all I need--
you to set my bloody kneecaps on fire.
I don't appreciate the insinuation, Longbottom.
Besides, if anyone cares to notice,
my eyebrows have completely grown back.
I found him!
"Dumbledore is particularly famous for his defeat
of the Dark Wizard Grindelwald in 1945--"
- Go on.
- "for his discovery of the 12 uses of dragon blood,
and his work on alchemy
with his partner Nicolas Flamel!"
HARRY: I knew the name sounded familiar.
I read it on the train that day.
Follow me!
Hey, wait! Where are you going?
What about the counter-curse?
I had you looking in the wrong section.
How could I be so stupid?
I checked this out weeks ago
for a bit of light reading.
This is light?
Of course! Here it is!
Nicolas Flamel is the only known
maker of the Philosopher's Stone.
The what?
Honestly, don't you two read?
"The Philosopher's Stone is a legendary
substance with astonishing powers.
It'll transform any metal
into pure gold...
...and produces the Elixir of Life,
which will make the drinker immortal."
- Immortal?
- It means you'll never die.
I know what it means!
"The only Stone currently in existence
belongs to Mr. Nicolas Flamel...
...the noted alchemist who last year
celebrated his 665th birthday."
That's what Fluffy's guarding.
That's what's under the trap door.
The Philosopher's Stone.
[KNOCKING]
Don't wish to be rude,
but I'm in no state to entertain.
ALL:
We know about the Philosopher's Stone.
Oh.
- We think Snape's trying to steal it.
- Are you still on about him?
We know he's after it.
We don't know why.
Snape is one of the teachers
protecting the Stone. He won't steal it.
What?
You heard. Come on,
I'm a bit preoccupied today.
HARRY: Wait a minute.
"One of the teachers"?
There are other things
defending the Stone, aren't there?
- Spells, enchantments.
HAGRID: Right.
Waste of bloody time, if you ask me.
Ain't no one gonna get past Fluffy.
Ain't a soul knows how,
except for me and Dumbledore.
I shouldn't have told you that.
I should not have told you that.
[RATTLING]
- Hagrid, what exactly is that?
- That? It's...
I know what that is!
But, Hagrid, how did you get one?
I won it. Off a stranger
I met down at the pub.
Seemed quite glad to be rid of it,
as a matter of fact.
Is that...
...a dragon?
That's not just a dragon.
That's a Norwegian Ridgeback.
My brother works
with these in Romania.
Isn't he beautiful? Oh, bless him.
Look, he knows his mummy.
Hello, Norbert.
- Norbert?
- He's gotta have a name, don't he?
Don't you, Norbert?
He'll have to be trained up a bit,
of course.
[DRAGON CRIES]
Who's that?
Malfoy.
Oh, dear.
HARRY: Hagrid always wanted a dragon.
Told me so the first time I met him.
RON: It's crazy.
And worse, Malfoy knows.
HARRY: I don't understand. Is that bad?
- It's bad.
Good evening.
Nothing, I repeat, nothing...
...gives a student the right
to walk about at night.
Therefore, as punishment for your
actions, 50 points will be taken.
- 50?!
- Each.
To ensure it doesn't happen again...
...all four of you
will receive detention.
Excuse me, professor,
perhaps I heard you wrong.
I thought you said the four of us.
No, you heard me correctly.
Honorable as your intentions were,
you too were out of bed after hours.
You will join your classmates
in detention.
FILCH: A pity they let
the old punishments die.
Was a time detention found you
hanging by your thumbs in the dungeons.
God, I miss the screaming.
You'll be serving detention
with Hagrid tonight.
He's got a little job to do
inside the Dark Forest.
A sorry lot, this, Hagrid.
Good God, you're not still on
about that bloody dragon, are you?
Norbert's gone.
Dumbledore sent him off to Romania
to live in a colony.
That's good, isn't it?
He's with his own kind.
What if he don't like Romania?
What if the other dragons are mean
to him? He's only a baby.
For God's sake, pull yourself together.
You're going into the Forest.
Got to have your wits about you.
The Forest? I thought that was a joke.
We can't go in there.
Students aren't allowed.
And there are...
[WOLF HOWLS]
...werewolves.
There's more than werewolves
in those trees.
You can be sure of that.
Nighty-night.
Right. Let's go.
[WOLF HOWLS]
Hagrid, what is that?
What we're here for.
See that?
That's unicorn blood, that is.
I found one dead a few weeks ago.
Now, this one's been hurt bad
by something.
[LEAVES RUSTLING]
So, it's our job to go
and find the poor beast.
- Ron, Hermione, come with me.
- Okay.
And, Harry, you'll go with Malfoy.
Okay. Then I get Fang.
Fine. Just so you know,
he's a bloody coward.
[FANG WHINES]
Wait till my father hears
about this. This is servant's stuff.
If I didn't know better,
I'd say you were scared.
All right, here we are in the Forbidden Forest.
Now, this is an interesting sequence
because we actually shot
the beginning of the sequence
in a real forest outside of London,
and shot at night, filled it with fog,
and really wanted to create this sense of mystery.
And as we get further into the forest,
we move onto a set
that we built on the Leavesden soundstage.
It was a fairly big set.
It was very impressive, actually.
We brought in all these real trees,
all these roots.
And Stuart Craig, again, outdid himself
because this feels like
a very, very real location.
This is the first time
that Harry encounters Voldemort.
Well, who we know is Quirrell
later in the picture.
But drinking unicorn blood,
and this proved to be a challenge
because unicorn blood
is supposed to be silver.
Obviously we couldn't put mercury
in anyone's mouth.
And that's the only liquid
that has that metallic look.
So what we did is we put
green liquid in our actor's mouth
and then we changed it
to that silvery sort of look.
Again, as you can probably tell,
this was done practically
with an actor on wires
who stood up and walked close to Harry.
At this point, we didn't really have
a definitive idea of what Voldemort
was gonna look like.
And I thought it was more frightening for
the audience if they didn't see his face at this point.
This was a very scary scene.
This first part was really done
without the benefit of visual effects,
and then, of course,
the centaur comes into the scene.
[HOOVES BEATING]
Harry Potter, you must leave.
You are known to many creatures here.
The Forest is not safe at this time.
Especially for you.
What was that thing you saved me from?
A monstrous creature.
It is a terrible crime to slay a unicorn.
Drinking its blood will keep you alive
even if you are an inch from death.
But at a terrible price. For you
have slain something so pure...
...that the moment the blood touches
your lips, you will have a half-life.
A cursed life.
Who would choose such a life?
COLUMBUS:
I think the centaur works beautifully here,
because he's mysterious,
he feels as if he's a real animal.
It's not just a human
attached to a horse body.
He feels like he's part of this beast
and he's towering and threatening.
The unicorn back there was actually built
by the person who did most of our prosthetics
in the movie, Nick Dudman.
A genius, Nick.
And Nick built a full-sized unicorn body
and brought it onto the set.
It was actually very sad
to see that unicorn lying there.
But again, our centaur here was voiced
by a very talented actor
from the Royal Shakespeare Company,
then he was completely animated
by a digital company in Los Angeles.
Good luck.
HERMIONE: You mean, You-Know-Who
is out there right now in the Forest?
But he's weak.
He's living off the unicorns.
Don't you see? We had it wrong.
Snape doesn't want the Stone
for himself. He wants it for Voldemort.
With the Elixir of Life,
Voldemort will be strong again.
He'll come back.
RON:
But if he comes back...
...you don't think he'll try
to kill you, do you?
If he'd had the chance,
he might have tried tonight.
And to think I've been worrying
about my Potions final.
HERMIONE: Hang on a minute.
We're forgetting one thing.
Who's the one wizard
Voldemort always feared?
Dumbledore. As long as Dumbledore
is around, Harry, you're safe.
As long as Dumbledore is around,
you can't be touched.
HERMIONE: I'd heard Hogwarts' final
exams were frightful, but that was fun.
Speak for yourself.
All right there, Harry?
- My scar. It keeps burning.
- It's happened before.
- Not like this.
RON: You should see the nurse.
HARRY: I think it's a warning.
It means danger's coming.
[FLUTE PLAYS]
- Of course!
- What is it?
Isn't it odd that what Hagrid wants
more than anything is a dragon...
...and a stranger just happens
to have one?
How many people wander around
with dragon eggs?
Why didn't I see it before?
Who gave you the egg?
What did he look like?
I never saw his face.
He kept his hood up.
You and this stranger
must have talked.
He wanted to know what sort
of creatures I looked after.
I said, "After Fluffy,
a dragon's gonna be no problem."
- Was he interested in Fluffy?
- Of course he was interested.
How often do you come across
a three-headed dog?
But I told him, "The trick with any beast
is to know how to calm him."
Take Fluffy, for example. Play him
music and he falls straight to sleep.
I shouldn't have told you that.
Where are you going?
We have to see Dumbledore.
Immediately!
I'm afraid he's not here.
He received an urgent owl
from the Ministry of Magic and left.
He's gone? But this is important!
This is about the Philosopher's Stone!
- How do you know--?
- Someone's going to try and steal it.
I don't know how you know,
but I assure you it is well protected.
Now would you go back
to your dormitories? Quietly.
That was no stranger Hagrid met.
It was Snape.
Which means he knows
how to get past Fluffy.
- And with Dumbledore gone--
- Good afternoon.
What would three young Gryffindors...
...be doing inside on a day like this?
- We were just--
- You ought to be careful.
People will think you're...
...up to something.
Now what do we do?
We go down the trap door. Tonight.
[TOAD CROAKS]
HARRY:
Trevor.
Trevor, go! You shouldn't be here!
Neither should you.
You're sneaking out again, aren't you?
- Neville, listen. We were--
- No, I won't let you!
You'll get Gryffindor into trouble again.
I'll fight you.
Neville, I'm really sorry about this.
Petrificus Totalus.
You're a little scary sometimes,
you know that?
Brilliant, but scary.
Let's go.
HERMIONE: Sorry.
RON: It's for your own good, you know.
- You stood on my foot!
- Sorry.
HERMIONE:
Alohomora.
HARRY:
Wait a minute. He's...
...snoring.
HARRY: Snape's already been here.
He's put a spell on the harp.
RON:
It's got horrible breath.
Here we have
our three-headed dog sequence.
This was a scene where we had to create
a CGI three-headed animal,
and I thought they did a wonderful job.
When they moved the paw, we created
a giant, furry paw for the kids to move.
But when they lifted it, practically,
the paw just looked like a giant stuffed animal.
So we had to literally draw over it
using our computer animation,
so when the kids lifted the paw
off of the trap door,
there was actually some movement
in the fingers,
and it felt like it was real
and it was alive.
I'll go first. Don't follow
until I give you a sign.
If something bad happens,
get yourselves out.
Does it seem a bit quiet to you?
The harp.
It's stopped playing.
Ugh. Yuck!
HARRY:
Jump!
[RON SCREAMS]
Whoa.
Lucky this plant thing's here, really.
Whoa!
HERMIONE: Stop moving, both of you.
This is Devil's Snare.
You have to relax. If you don't,
it will only kill you faster.
Kill us faster?
Oh, now I can relax!
COLUMBUS:
So for Devil's Snare,
I said, "Okay, let's us build Devil's Snare,
and I'll shoot it in a way that we don't
have to incorporate any digital effects.
I'll shoot it in reverse."
So all of these sequences are actually done
with real, practical puppeteers,
below the Devil's Snare set,
actually moving the tentacles
in each sequence.
And when the kids are wrapped
with the tentacles,
the kids were actually able
to act in reverse.
It's better than any CGI version of it
we could have ever done.
Because the kids, who needed it at the time,
as opposed to dealing with
just a green screen situation,
were actually able to act
with real, tangible effects
and it worked beautifully.
Lumus Solem.
And Hermione saves the day,
which is a huge moment.
Only visual effects shot is the shot of the wand
coming up through the Devil's Snare sequence,
through the Devil's Snare area.
And I love the fact that Hermione
has her moment there.
It's just a great, wonderful moment for her.
[WINGS FLUTTERING]
HERMIONE:
What is that?
I don't know. Sounds like wings.
HERMIONE: Curious.
I've never seen birds like these.
HARRY: They're not birds.
They're keys.
And I'll bet one of them
fits that door.
- What's this all about?
- I don't know.
Strange.
RON:
Alohomora!
Well, it was worth a try.
What will we do?
There must be a thousand keys.
RON: We want a big, old-fashioned one.
Probably rusty.
I see it!
The one with the broken wing.
What's wrong?
It's too simple.
Go on! If Snape could catch it
on that old broomstick, you can.
You're the youngest Seeker
in a century.
This complicates things a bit.
HARRY:
Catch the key!
Hurry up!
HERMIONE: I don't like this.
I don't like this at all.
Where are we? A graveyard.
This is no graveyard.
It's a chessboard.
Here we have Wizard's Chess, one of
the 50 sequences I was most excited about doing.
The great thing about these Harry Potter books
is that every sequence, as a director,
you're like a kid in a candy store.
But for me, this was an exciting sequence,
because we could have, again,
built all of this in a digital environment,
put the kids in a green-screen world,
but we didn't.
Stuart Craig built this entire set
and created each one of those chess pieces.
So, when you walked onto that set,
you saw all of these life-size chess pieces
and this chessboard surrounded by fire,
and it was amazing.
I mean, I was in awe
of what Stuart had done here.
I wanted to take several of the pieces
back to America with me
and put them up around my house,
I was so impressed.
They looked like these wonderful sculptures.
And we utilized CGI in certain elements.
When you see the pawns draw their swords,
those sort of things,
we utilized CGI to create a sense
of movement among the chess pieces.
But all of these other chess pieces are real.
And they even moved forward.
When Ron's chess piece moves forward here,
when he's making his tremendous sacrifice,
these were practical.
And the combined movement of the camera,
along with the pieces mechanically moving
along the floor,
created a real sense of terror
and a real suspenseful moment.
There was talk about
making them move more quickly,
and I just loved the fact
that this sequence happened
at its own pace.
One of my favorite shots in the movie
is Ron really deciding to sacrifice himself.
And that to me is just
an amazing performance by a kid
who was starting to feel
very comfortable with his character.
He sees the power of these things,
and he realizes he's gotta sacrifice himself
for his friends.
I sensed a real moment of fear
but also courage from Rupert at that point.
Probably his best performance in the film.
Castle to e4!
Pawn to c3!
- Wait a minute.
RON: You understand right, Harry.
Once I make my move,
the queen will take me.
Then you're free to check the king.
- No. Ron, no!
- What is it?
- He's going to sacrifice himself.
- No, there must be another way!
Do you wanna stop Snape
from getting that Stone or not?
Harry, it's you that has to go on.
I know it.
Not me. Not Hermione. You.
Knight to h3.
Check.
[RON SCREAMS]
Ron!
No, don't move!
Don't forget, we're still playing.
Checkmate.
Take care of Ron.
Then go to the owlery.
Send a message to Dumbledore.
Ron's right.
I have to go on.
You'll be okay, Harry.
You're a great wizard. You really are.
Not as good as you.
Me? Books and cleverness.
There are more important things.
Friendship and bravery.
And, Harry, just be careful.
You?
No, it can't be.
Snape, he was the--
QUIRRELL: Yes, he does seem the type,
doesn't he?
Next to him, who would suspect...
...poor, stuttering
Professor Quirrell?
But that day, during the Quidditch match,
Snape tried to kill me.
No, dear boy. I tried to kill you!
If Snape's cloak hadn't caught
fire and broken my eye contact...
...I would have succeeded.
Even with Snape muttering
his countercurse.
Snape was trying to save me?
I knew you were a danger to me,
especially after Halloween.
- Then you let the troll in!
- Very good, Potter, yes.
Snape, unfortunately, wasn't fooled.
While everyone ran about, he went
to the third floor to head me off.
He, of course, never trusted me again.
He rarely left me alone.
But he doesn't understand.
I'm never alone. Never.
Now, what does this mirror do?
I see what I desire.
I see myself holding the Stone.
But how do I get it?
MAN:
Use the boy.
Come here, Potter! Now!
Tell me, what do you see?
What is it? What do you see?
I'm shaking hands with Dumbledore.
I've won the house cup.
MAN:
He lies.
Tell the truth! What do you see?
MAN: Let me speak to him.
- Master, you are not strong enough.
MAN:
I have strength enough for this.
Very interesting scene here.
This is our first reveal of Voldemort
in any of the films.
This was prior to the casting of Ralph Fiennes
so ironically, in a weird way,
this Voldemort kind of resembles
the Ralph Fiennes you see in the later pictures.
I always thought I would want to go back--
again, as a director,
you always want to go back--
want to go back and reshoot this,
or reshoot that particular part of it,
so the films would have a real consistency.
It would be great to reshoot it
with Ralph Fiennes' voice and look now.
This is pretty close.
But it's not exactly where we are
in the later pictures.
But for a visual effect at the time,
I was very impressed
at what our visual effects department
came up with here.
Because it was a concept
that was quite odd.
Only Jo Rowling could have come up with the fact
that Voldemort appears
out of the back of a man's head.
It's kind of a grotesque and fascinating idea.
How do you do it?
Well, we had our actor wearing
little green dots on the back of his head,
and then Voldemort was added much later.
I was just intrigued by this sequence,
because I thought it would be so horrifying.
And we wanted to make it fairly horrifying
for the little kiddies out there.
I thought it would be so horrifying
that the film would get a PG-13,
which is not what we wanted
on the first Potter film.
But for some reason,
kids weren't running out of the theater.
They were emotionally invested
in the film at this point.
Because I think there was
an emotional quality here.
When you combine Harry's parents
along with this hideous Voldemort face,
I think that you sort of temper it a little bit,
you soften it a little for the kids in the audience.
The casting of Harry's parents was difficult
because we knew they would be
in subsequent pictures,
but at this point, we hadn't read all the books,
so we didn't know if they would appear
in book five, six, seven.
We had no idea.
And Jo really didn't give us
that particular information.
So we cast people who have since
appeared in subsequent pictures,
and we didn't know if they would get to speak
or how much we would get to know them.
This was done with-- again, we built this set.
That's all real fire in the background,
again, in an effort to give the kids a sense
of tangible things they could hold onto.
- What is this magic?
- Fool, get the Stone!
Our actor here who played Quirrell,
was there for Dan all the time.
Obviously, when his face is burning
and disintegrating, these are all CGI effects.
To do this practically
would probably hurt someone.
We didn't do that.
This was a little homage
to one of my favorite pictures from the late '50s,
Horror of Dracula, one of the Hammer films,
where Christopher Lee disintegrates at the end.
I think I even borrowed a shot
from that final sequence,
where Christopher Lee is defeated
by Peter Cushing.
And our stone, the big moment in our movie,
the Sorcerer's Stone, the Philosopher's Stone,
was really created out of plastic.
We had several of these
that were made by our prop department.
Sometimes they looked like candy.
They weren't shiny enough.
And the only way we could ever get
the sense of a reflection
was to put a reflection
of a flame in there.
Voldemort here is obviously created
through a CGI effect,
which was very effective.
Again, in Jo's world, which is so wonderful
and imaginative and amazing,
Voldemort actually has to pass through Harry,
which I just thought was something
I'd never seen before.
Good afternoon, Harry.
- Tokens from your admirers?
- Admirers?
What happened in the dungeons between
you and Professor Quirrell is a secret.
So, naturally, the whole school knows.
I see that your friend Ronald
has saved you the trouble...
...of opening your Chocolate Frogs.
Ron was here? Is he all right?
What about Hermione?
Fine. They're both just fine.
- What happened to the Stone?
- Relax, dear boy.
The Stone has been destroyed.
My friend Nicolas and I
have had a little chat...
...and agreed it was best all around.
But then, Flamel,
he'll die, won't he?
He has enough Elixir
to set his affairs in order.
But yes, he will die.
How is it I got the Stone, sir?
One minute I was staring
in the mirror and--
You see, only a person...
...who wanted to find the Stone,
find it...
...but not use it,
would be able to get it.
That is one of my more brilliant ideas.
And between you and me,
that is saying something.
Does that mean, with the Stone gone,
that Voldemort can never come back?
I'm afraid...
...there are ways
in which he can return.
Harry, do you know why...
...Professor Quirrell couldn't bear
to have you touch him?
It was because of your mother.
She sacrificed herself for you.
And that kind of act leaves a mark.
No, this kind of mark cannot be seen.
- It lives in your very skin.
- What is it?
Love, Harry. Love.
Bertie Bott's Every Flavor Beans.
I was most unfortunate in my youth
to come across a vomit-flavored one.
And since then,
I've lost my liking for them.
But I think I could be safe...
...with a nice toffee.
Hm, alas!
Earwax.
- All right there, Ron?
- All right. You?
All right. Hermione?
Never better.
Another year gone.
And now, as I understand it,
the house cup needs awarding.
And the points stand thus:
In fourth place,
Gryffindor with 312 points.
Third place,
Hufflepuff with 352 points.
In second place...
...Ravenclaw with 426 points.
And in first place...
...with 472 points, Slytherin house.
Nice one, mate.
Yes, well done, Slytherin.
Well done.
However, recent events must
be taken into account.
And I have a few last-minute points
to award.
To Miss Hermione Granger,
for the cool use of intellect...
...while others were in grave peril...
...50 points.
Good job.
Second, to Mr. Ronald Weasley,
for the best-played game of chess...
...that Hogwarts has seen
these many years, 50 points.
And third...
...to Mr. Harry Potter...
...for pure nerve
and outstanding courage...
...I award Gryffindor house 60 points.
We're tied with Slytherin!
Finally, it takes a great deal of bravery
to stand up to your enemies...
...but a great deal more
to stand up to your friends.
I award 10 points...
...to Neville Longbottom.
Assuming that my calculations
are correct...
...I believe that a change
of decoration is in order.
Gryffindor wins the house cup.
Yes!
We won!
[TRAIN WHISTLE BLOWS]
HAGRID: Come on, now.
Hurry up, you'll be late.
Train's leaving. Go on.
Come on, hurry up.
- Come on, Harry.
- One minute.
Thought you were leaving
without saying goodbye, did you?
This is for you.
Thanks, Hagrid.
Go on. On with you. On with you now.
Oh, listen, Harry.
If that dolt of a cousin of yours,
Dudley, gives you any grief...
...you could always threaten him...
...with a nice pair of ears
to go with his tail.
But we're not allowed to do magic
away from Hogwarts. You know that.
I do. But your cousin don't, do he?
COLUMBUS: Dan's first spoken line
in a Harry Potter movie
comes when he says,
"I'm not going home. Not really."
I'm not going home.
Not really.
And when he says that,
when I saw the dailies to that,
I was actually very touched.
I had tears in my eyes.
I looked over at David Heyman.
He's got tears in his eyes.
And I said, "How is it this kid came up
with such a very unsentimental, real performance?"
And that is just a testament
to Dan's ability as an actor,
even from the very first day on this film.
I hope you guys had
a wonderful time watching this.
I could talk about this forever,
so, thank you so much.
This has been a real pleasure for me
to revisit the world of Harry Potter,
which means so much to me. Thanks.
NARRATOR:
Well, there were a few close calls,
mean monsters,
poisonous professors and wicked wizards.
But Harry, Ron and Hermione
survived their first year at Hogwarts.
Now how did you fare?
Time to add up your points.
To begin, let's see where
the Golden Snitch was buzzing about.
Didn't waste any time, I see.
A cozy common room,
can't say I blame you.
A-ha! Easy-peasy.
It would take a Seeker
to get you up there.
Sneaky little Snitch, aren't you?
Hello, hello, hello.
Right then, award yourself 25 points
for every Snitch you spotted.
And onto the Hogwarts Trivia Challenge.
Score five points for every question
you answered correctly.
Go on, add them up.
Now, if you scored
between five and 100 points,
tut-tut, better luck next time.
Here, perhaps a Remembrall
will come in handy.
Or a dozen.
If you scored between 105 and 200 points,
well done!
Smarter than a Mountain Troll,
but a bit short of Hermione Granger.
Nevertheless, a chocolate frog for you.
If you scored between 205 and 300 points...
Brilliant! You know your Harry Potter.
That deserves your very own Nimbus 2000.
And if you scored a perfect score,
all 300 points...
hmm, could it be?
Could it be?
Bravo! You win the house cup!
Alas, that's all the magic
we have for now...
until our next year at Hogwarts.
[GIGGLES]